Guide to the Thomas F. De Voe Scrapbooks circa 1720-1890 (bulk, 1850s-1880s) MS 3193
New-York Historical Society
Thomas F. De Voe scrapbooks
circa 1720-1890 (Bulk, 1850s-1880s)
New-York Historical Society
De Voe, Thomas F. (Thomas Farrington), 1811-1892
MS 3193
19 Linear feet in 19 boxes
The collection includes 80 scrapbooks compiled by Thomas F. De Voe (1811-1892). The bulk of the content is newspaper clippings, though some other printed forms are present as well. Some material ranges as early as circa 1720 and as late as 1890, but the bulk ranges from the 1850s into the 1880s. 34 of the volumes concern New York City history (e.g., politics, built environment, cultural institutions, events, etc.); 15 volumes relate to obituaries or other profiles of notable people; 8 relate to the Civil War and other military matters; 7 concern markets; and the remaining 16 volumes are on various topics.
Access Restrictions
Materials in this collection are stored offsite. For more information on making arrangements to consult them, please visit www.nyhistory.org/library/visit.
Arrangement
Although notations on many of the volumes suggest that there was an overall structure to at least many of De Voe's compilations, that structure is no longer fully discernible. Labeled spines are now missing, some items may have been separated from the collection, perhaps not all volumes were received by N-YHS, and other factors complicate any arrangement to original order. Consequently, the 80 volumes in this collection have been arranged roughly by subject matter as perceived by the N-YHS archivist in May 2022. The rough categories are:
Markets (7 volumes)
Obituaries (15 volumes)
Civil War and other military matters (8 volumes)
New York City historical matters (21 volumes)
New York City matters of the mid to late 19th century (13 volumes)
Miscellaneous subjects (16 volumes)
Each scrapbook was given a unique identifier (e.g., SN-1, SN-2) by the processing archivists in 2022. These are intended only to facilitate reference and are not indicative of any overall numbering scheme found in the collection itself.
Biographical / Historical
Thomas F. De Voe was born in 1811 in Westchester County, New York. He apprenticed as a butcher, then operated his own business at the Jefferson Market at 6th Avenue and Christopher Street in Manhattan from 1833 to 1872. In 1840, his fellow Jefferson Market butchers chose De Voe to represent them to the city on regulatory matters. To do this work more effectively, De Voe did research, including at New-York Historical Society, where he eventually became a member. With the encouragement of N-YHS Librarian George Moore and others, De Voe turned his research into the published works he is well-known for: "The Market Book" (1862), a historical account of New York's markets, and "The Market Assistant" (1867), a description of the foods available at the markets. De Voe was also an officer of the New York State militia's 8th Regiment. In 1872, De Voe gave up his business to become New York City's Superintendent of Markets. He died in 1892.
(The above note was largely based on an article about De Voe in the Spring-Summer 2008 issue of "The Quarto," a publication of the University of Michigan's Clements Library Associates.)
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Bequest of Thomas F. De Voe.
Related Materials
New-York Historical Society holds many collections by or related to Thomas De Voe. These can be identified by searching on De Voe's name in N-YHS's on-line catalog, Bobcat. It is likely that at least some of those documents are closely related to these scrapbooks, but were separated for item level cataloging and shelved separately at some point. Many of these separate collections relate substantially to De Voe's interest in markets.
Scope and Contents
The collection includes 80 scrapbooks compiled by Thomas De Voe. The bulk of the content is newspaper clippings, though some other printed forms are present as well. Some material ranges as early as circa 1720 and as late as 1890, but the bulk ranges from the 1850s into the 1880s. A few of the volumes are indexes to scrapbooks of clippings, which may or may not be in this collection. Entries in the container list that begin with the word Index indicate these.
34 of the volumes concern either New York City history (that is, from De Voe's perspective looking back from the mid-19th century) or contemporary developments during the 1850s to 1880s. These latter volumes include a variety of subject matter about the development of New York (especially Manhattan), such as in transportation (ferries, railways, etc.), cultural institutions (museums, historical societies), infrastructure (streets), events, etc. 15 volumes relate to obituaries or other profiles of notable people, 8 relate to the Civil War and other military matters, 7 concern markets, and the remaining 16 volumes are on various topics.
Each volume is listed in the container list. Volumes that retain a title given them by De Voe are noted in "quotations." Volumes that have a title given them over time by someone at N-YHS (possibly taken from a now missing original De Voe label) are noted in [brackets]. Volumes listed with no such markings were titled by the processing archivist in 2022 for the inventory; in these cases the volume had no indication of a title and the archivist assigned one based on a skim of the content.
Existence and Location of Copies
There are bound facsimiles of volumes SN-67, SN-68, SN-79, and another copy of Mariam Touba's index (see SN-68) available at the reference desk.
Newspaper clippings.; Obituaries; Research notes.; Scrapbooks.; New York (N.Y.) -- History.; New York (State) -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865.; Markets -- New York (State) -- New York.
- Markets, 1850-1883 (Offsite-box 9, Volume SN-56)
  Scope and Contents
  Includes, among others, articles about De Voe's book.
- "Markets & Collections", 1854-1858, 1860s (Offsite-box 11, Volume SN-57)
  Relates especially to the beef/cattle market. Bulk is from 1854-1858.
- Markets, 1854-1856, 1870s? (Offsite-box 18, Volume SN-77)
  The volume holds clippings from 1854-1856. At the back of the volume is a manuscript list of notes on markets opened in New York City, 1836-1871.
- New York Markets, 1876-1887 (Offsite-box 12, Volume SN-55)
- New York City Markets, 1864-1874 (Offsite-box 14, Volume SN-71)
- Extracts of articles on cattle, poultry, fish, etc. (manuscript ), undated (Offsite-box 15, Volume SN-72)
- [Philadelphia Markets], 1790s-1880s (Offsite-box 12, Volume SN-63)
- Index. "Book G." [Obituaries, 1869-1873] (Offsite-box 2, Volume SN-17)
- [Obituaries, New York City & Elsewhere. Index G], 1866-1873 (Offsite-box 12, Volume SN-66)
- Index. "Obituaries of Noted Persons, 1869-1878. 37" (Offsite-box 2, Volume SN-29)
- "Obituaries of Noted Persons. Index No. 37", 1869-1878 (Offsite-box 5, Volume SN-13)
- Index. "Book P. Prominent Persons Obituaries, 1866-1868" (Offsite-box 2, Volume SN-18)
- Index. "U" [Obituaries, 1878-1881] (Offsite-box 2, Volume SN-23)
- Obituaries, 1878-1881 (Offsite-box 6, Volume SN-21)
- Index. "Obituaries, 1881-1882. 26" (Offsite-box 2, Volume SN-20)
- Obituaries, 1881-1882 (Offsite-box 7, Volume SN-19)
  The bulk of this volume holds clippings about the assassination of President James Garfield.
- Index. "Obituaries, 1881-1883. 3" (Offsite-box 2, Volume SN-28)
- "Obituaries from 1881-1883" (Offsite-box 3, Volume SN-27)
- "Index to No. 39. Obituaries, 1884-1886" (Offsite-box 2, Volume SN-15)
- Obituaries, 1884-1886 (Offsite-box 6, Volume SN-22)
- Obituaries, 1886-1889 (Offsite-box 16, Volume SN-75)
- Obituaries, 1887-1891 (Offsite-box 17, Volume SN-74)
- [Military clippings. #19], 1854-1855 (Offsite-box 1, Volume SN-10)
- New York State Militia/National Guard, 1857-1860 (Offsite-box 10, Volume SN-43)
  Includes, among other subjects, articles on yellow fever quarantine on Staten Island.
- New York State Militia/National Guard, 1860-1862 (Offsite-box 10, Volume SN-44)
  Primarily holds articles about the Civil War
- New York State Militia/National Guard, 1863-1880s (Offsite-box 14, Volume SN-70)
- Civil War, 1861-1863, 1886 (Offsite-box 14, Volume SN-69)
  The clippings all date from the 1860s. There is one drawing of the Statue of Liberty, dated 1886.
- Civil War, 1860s-1880s (Offsite-box 14, Volume SN-49)
  Principally about the Civil War and later reminiscences.
- Civil War and New York City current events, 1854, 1861-1870 (Offsite-box 11, Volume SN-45)
- [Military & Naval Clippings] & Theatre, 1879-1890 (Offsite-box 8, Volume SN-39)
- "Index to Historical Incidents from Newspapers, 1696-1800"; "Index to Names of Persons from Newspapers, 1696-1800", undated (Offsite-box 18, Volume SN-79)
  These appear to be alphabetical subject indexes to the chronology above (SN-67). There is a bound facsimile of this volume available at the reference desk.
- "Historical Incidents from Newspapers I, 1696-1800" (manuscript), undated (Offsite-box 16, Volume SN-67)
  The volume is a year by year chronology of events, in manuscript form, abstracted by De Voe from newspapers. There are letters related to the De Voe collection generally, attached to the back cover. There is a bound facsimile of this volume available at the reference desk.
- "Historical Incidents from Newspapers II, 1800-1850" (manuscript), undated (Offsite-box 16, Volume SN-68)
  This volume has the same general content as I (SN-67) above. This box also holds a related draft index for the years 1800-1810 prepared by N-YHS reference librarian Mariam Touba. There is a bound facsimile of this volume and a copy of Touba's index available at the reference desk.
- Index. "Miscellaneous scraps from 1720-1828. 100", undated (Offsite-box 2, Volume SN-53)
- "Miscellaneous scraps, 1720-1828" (Offsite-box 4, Volume SN-34)
  This volume holds original clippings. SN-53 may be an index to this volume.
- "History of New York" (9 volumes), 1851-1870 (Offsite-box 1, Volume SN-1 to SN-9)
  These volumes hold clippings of compilations about New York City history by "DTV" (David T. Valentine). The original source of the clippings is not explicit, except for 1868-70, which are from Valentine's Manual of the Corporation of New York City; this is the likely source for most or all of the other clippings in these 9 volumes.
- Index. "Olden Time in New York. Bacon. T" [1-123], undated (Offsite-box 2, Volume SN-31)
- "Cuttings. T" [Index T. New York in the Olden Time by J.B. Bacon. 1-123], undated (Offsite-box 3, Volume SN-30)
- Index. "F" [Old New York, 1870-1875] (Offsite-box 2, Volume SN-42)
- Old New York-related clippings, 1876-1877 (Offsite-box 2, Volume SN-52)
- Index. "Old New York. 61", undated (Offsite-box 2, Volume SN-41)
- [Old New York #7, 1871-1875] (Offsite-box 3, Volume SN-33)
- New York City history, 1860s-1880s (Offsite-box 9, Volume SN-32)
- General clippings about New York, 1849-1861 (Offsite-box 15, Volume SN-73)
  Holds clippings about catastrophes, current events, city development, etc.
- General clippings about New York, 1853-1863 (Offsite-box 18, Volume SN-78)
- General clippings about New York, 1863-1873 (Offsite-box 18, Volume SN-76)
- General clippings about New York City, 1869-1875 (Offsite-box 3, Volume SN-14)
- General clippings about New York City, 1870-1875 (Offsite-box 1, Volume SN-12)
- General clippings about New York, 1871-1885 (Offsite-box 17, Volume SN-64)
- "Index. Streets, Lanes, Roads, etc., Wharves & Piers. No. 43", undated (Offsite-box 2, Volume SN-40)
- "New York City covering Manhattan Island, newspaper clippings, 1877-1890" (Offsite-box 4, Volume SN-38)
- Miscellaneous, especially theatre/stage, 1868-1869, 1881-1890 (Offsite-box 6, Volume SN-46)
  Many pages of a cash journal from 1868-1869 are visible in this volume as, unlike other volumes, it was not entirely covered over with clippings.
- General clippings about New York, 1851-1858, 1866-1870 (Offsite-box 8, Volume SN-25)
- "Andrew H. Green for Mayor; Trials of Prominent Persons; New York City", 1869-1889 (Offsite-box 5, Volume SN-11)
  The volume especially holds clippings about the Albert D. Richardson murder (1869) and the Henry Ward Beecher-Elizabeth Tilton matter (1870s). There is only a little about Andrew H. Green.
- New York City and State Politics, 1871-1872 (Offsite-box 13, Volume SN-65)
  Holds articles about Boss Tweed, Tammany Hall, city charter, legislation, etc.
- Miscellaneous, especially politics, 1875-1878 (Offsite-box 7, Volume SN-16)
  Holds clippings on Boss Tweed, Tammany Hall, Andrew Green, etc. Holds the lengthy reminiscences of the former New York mayor M.M. Noah.
- Catastrophes, 1846-1873 (Offsite-box 12, Volume SN-62)
  Articles about ship sinkings, fires, weather, murders, riots, etc.
- [E. Strikes & Riots, 1877] (Offsite-box 4, Volume SN-47)
- "United States. E" [Strikes & Riots, 1877] (Offsite-box 2, Volume SN-48)
- [Catastrophes. 13], 1880-1888 (Offsite-box 8, Volume SN-24)
  The clippings' geographic range extends beyond New York.
- "J" [Churches & Ministers, 1874-1883] (Offsite-box 2, Volume SN-60)
- Churches and other houses of religious worship, clergy, 1870s-1880s (Offsite-box 4, Volume SN-37)
- Churches and other houses of religious worship, and clergy, 1863-1890 (Offsite-box 12, Volume SN-59)
  The clippings in the volume date from 1883-1890. Many pages were not covered in clippings and so the underlying content is readable. It presumably pertains to the firm S. Judd's Sons & Co., the name embossed on the volume's cover. Entries from 1863 and the 1870s concern the creditworthiness of various companies. For 1863, these are New York State companies; for the 1870s, companies elsewhere in the United States.
- Index. "O. Historical Items & Obituaries, etc., 1858-1874" (Offsite-box 2, Volume SN-36)
- [Historical Items & Obituaries, etc., 1858-1874] (Offsite-box 4, Volume SN-35)
- Index. "Personal in New York, 1875, 1879. 55" (Offsite-box 2, Volume SN-50)
- Various clippings about people and events, 1860s-1870s (Offsite-box 3, Volume SN-26)
  Holds obituaries and other articles about people, portraits of clergy, and various events. Geographic range goes beyond New York.
- Clippings about current events, 1854-1870, 1883-1889 (Offsite-box 4, Volume SN-54)
- Index. "71" [Brooklyn Newspapers], undated (Offsite-box 2, Volume SN-51)
- Miscellaneous, 1860s-1880s (Offsite-box 13, Volume SN-80)
  Holds articles about travel description, current events, speeches, international matters, etc.
- Miscellaneous, 1850s-1860s (Offsite-box 11, Volume SN-58)
  This volume was found on the shelves in 2022 with the De Voe scrapbooks, but it may not be one of his. The volume holds various articles, many concerning slavery and other topical matters. Many of the articles are signed "Sigma" and are from the Daily Evening Traveler. A table of contents is at the front. There appears to be an accession date of March 18, 1897, on the cover, which would include it among the many donations made that day by Daniel Parish.
- Miscellaneous, 1854-1857 (Offsite-box 12, Volume SN-61)
  Holds mostly clippings of the series "Letters from New York" signed by "Roscoe" to the "Editors of the Traveller" (i.e., Daily Evening Traveller of Boston). There are also clippings of reviews and other articles about R.G. Horton's "Life & Public Service of James Buchanan."
- Loose book spines, undated (Offsite-box 19)
  Several book spines with labels that had loose from the original volumes. These were found shelved separately after the collection had been boxed for storage and so were not (and perhaps cannot be) matched to the related volumes.